A Finding Aid to the Area Gallery Records, 1958-1977, bulk 1959-1964, in the Archives of American Art AAA.areagall
Archives of American Art
Area Gallery records
bulk 1959-1964
1958-1977
AAA.areagall
Archives of American Art
1.1 Linear feet
The records of the Area Gallery measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1958-1977 (bulk dates 1959-1964). Area Gallery was one of the Tenth Street Co-ops in New York City, and operated from 1958-1965. Materials in this collection include artist bios, price lists, black and white photos of artwork; financial records with annotations; member lists, exhibition lists, and daily notes; gallery sign-in sheets; correspondence, including letters to and from the gallery and regarding rent issues; and an extensive scrapbook containing exhibition posters, photos of artwork, announcements, exhibition reviews, and clippings.
Area Gallery (New York, N.Y.).
Related Archival Materials note
Also found in the Archives of American Art is a collection relating to the Tenth Street Galleries and collection donor, Ruth Fortel. See: Joellen Bard's, Ruth Fortel's, and Helen Thomas' exhibition records of "Tenth Street Days: the Co-ops of the 50s," 1953-1977.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the Area Gallery measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1958-1977 (bulk dates 1959-1964). Area Gallery was one of the Tenth Street Co-ops in New York City, and operated from 1958-1965. Materials in this collection include artist bios, price lists, black and white photos of artwork; financial records with annotations; member lists, exhibition lists, and daily notes; gallery sign-in sheets; correspondence, including letters to and from the gallery and regarding rent issues; and an extensive scrapbook containing exhibition posters, photos of artwork, announcements, exhibition reviews, and clippings.
Administrative records contain member lists, daily operational notes and messages, artwork loan contracts to museums, some mail received by the gallery, and all sign-in sheets for the gallery from 1962-1965. It is noted that all sign-in sheets prior to April 1962 have been lost.
Correspondence is primarily to and from the Treasurer of Area Gallery, and also contains requests for hire and exhibitions, member resignations, payments made and received. Additionally, rent correspondence contains letters regarding late or overdue payments.
The artist files and scrapbook contain black and white photographs of artwork, artist bios, price lists, and some exhibition announcements, and represent a small fraction of the number of artists who showed at Area Gallery. The scrapbook also contains exhibition review clippings and exhibition posters.
The financial records include cancelled checks, many of which have been annotated, deposit slips and bank statements, also annotated. Receipts for bills, supplies, artist payments, and dues are also included, as well as two bookkeeping ledgers.
Biographical/Historical note
Area Gallery was one of the Tenth Street Co-ops in New York City, and operated from 1958-1965. From fall 1958 to summer 1962, the gallery was located at 80 East 10th Street, and then moved to 90 East 10th Street until the summer of 1965. Area Gallery’s original members were: Tom Boutis, John Ireland Collins, Charles DuBack, Joe Fiore, Bernard Langlais, Ed Moses, Daphne Mumford, and Paul Yakovenko.
New York’s Tenth Street Galleries were a cooperative of artist-run galleries that began opening in the early 1950s, located between 3rd and 4th Avenues, where spaces for living and studios were relatively inexpensive. It was the center for anything new and avant-garde in downtown Manhattan at this time. Galleries operated on very low budgets, artists were often members of more than one gallery, and they provided an alternative to the highly selective Madison Avenue and 57th Street galleries. The top galleries of the 10th Street Co-ops were the Tanager, Hansa, James, Camino, March, Phoenix, Brata, and Area Gallery.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The records were donated in 1978 by Ruth Becker Fortel, Treasurer of Area Gallery.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 5 series.
Series 1: Administrative Records, 1958-1977 (8 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1958-1965 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Artist Files, 1959-1964 (15 folders; Box 1)
Series 4: Financial Records, 1958-1965 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 5: Scrapbook, 1959-1966 (0.3 linear feet; Box 3)
Art galleries, Cooperative--New York (State)--New York; Photographs; Scrapbooks
- Administrative Records, 1958-1977; Series 1; 8 Folders Box 1
  Arrangement note
  Folders are arranged as found upon donation, many items were already arranged chronologically within folders.
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative records document the daily functions of the Area Gallery. Included are vital statistics, which contain member lists, exhibition lists, and artist biographies, and also price lists for exhibitions. Additionally there are daily notes, communicating messages from artists and studio occupants as well as operational issues and an annotated calendar/day planner. Also found are artwork loan contracts and various mail solicitings. The sign-in sheets from April 1962 until 1965 provide signed listings of who visited the gallery daily and for exhibitions. Of note, artist Marcel Duchamp has signed-in for the Gordon Press Show in 1962. In 1963, Italian architect Mario Bellini makes an appearance, as well as Ad Reinhardt and Mark Rothko in 1964.
  The gallery also notes that all sign-in sheets prior to April 1962 have been lost.
  - Vital Statistics - Member Lists, Exhibition Lists, Artist Bios, 1958-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Price Lists - Shows, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Daily Notes - Messages Taken, Operational Notes, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Calendar/Day Planner - Annotated, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Artwork Loan Contracts, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mail - Solicitings, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Sign-in Sheets, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Sign-in Sheets, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Correspondence, 1958-1965; Series 2; 3 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence is varied and includes handwritten and typewritten letters to and from the gallery. The subject of correspondence ranges from artists requesting exhibitions to requests for payment of membership dues to letters inquiring about gallery members. Additionally, a separate folder contains correspondence solely pertaining to the gallery’s rent costs.
  - Miscellaneous, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, 1964-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Rent, 1958-1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Artist Files, 1959-1964; Series 3; 15 Folders Box 1
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by artist's last name.
  Artist files contain black and white photographs of artwork, price lists, and artist bios. Researchers should note that the folder for Ellen Leelike also contains 1 black and white photograph of Harvey Becker's artwork, and the folder for Philip Russell contains 1 black and white photograph of Antonio Rubino's artwork. Also of note, this series contains one unidentified charcoal sketch.
  - Boutis, Tom, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Brown, Lydia, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Cohen, Arthur, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Collings, John Ireland, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - DuBack, Charles, circa 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fortel, Ruth Becker, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Leelike, Ellen, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Mason, Emily, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Matthews, Doris, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Mumford, Daphne G., circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Russell, Philip, 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Valenti, Nadine, circa 1962 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Windust, Marjorie, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Yakovenko, Paul, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Unidentified Charcoal Sketch, circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Financial Records, 1958-1965; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Folders are arranged as found upon donation, and chronologically arranged by the donor.
  Financial records document the monetary activities of the gallery's operations. Found here are bank account statements, bookkeeping ledgers, deposit slips, cancelled checks, receipts, and financial statistics and projections. Most of these contain annotations and notes as to the function of the receipt, check, deposit slip, and provide a more complete look at the operational activities and financial viability of the gallery.
  - Bookkeeping - Ledger, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Bookkeeping - Ledger, 1958-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bookkeeping - Financial Statistics & Projections, Posted Sublet Ad Clippings, Miscellaneous Notes, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Bank Statements, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Cancelled Checks - To New York Telephone Co., To Con Edison, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Cancelled Checks - Rent, 1959-1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Cancelled Checks - Printing & Stamps, Miscellaneous, 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Cancelled Checks - To Artists, 1959-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Cancelled Checks - To Artists, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Deposit Slips - Dues, etc., 1959-1964 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
  - Receipts - Advertising, Coal, Electric, 1958-1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Receipts - Founders' Receipts, 1958-circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Receipts - Gallery Equipment & Repairs, 1958-1964 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Receipts - Printing, Telephone, Wine, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Scrapbook, 1959-1966; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 3
  Materials are arranged chronologically with pages of the scrapbook free from their original binding.
  The scrapbook contains a variety of materials concerning Area Gallery, including exhibition posters and announcements, newspaper clippings of exhibition reviews, black and white photographs of artists and artwork, and some annotations.
  - Scrapbook, 1959-1966 (Box 3)